<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>[Elephant and His Friend Nbali]</title>
        <editor ref="p:Putnam19" role="collector">Anne Putnam</editor>
        <editor ref="p:unidentified0" role="narrator">unidentified</editor>
        <funder>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</funder>
        <principal>
          <persName>Katja Mellmann</persName>
          <persName>Michelle Scalise Sugiyama</persName>
        </principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>XML template, digitization architecture, and automated inline tagging</resp>
          <persName>Jan Jokisch</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <extent>
        <measure unit="KB" quantity="9">About 9 kilobytes</measure>
      </extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Forager Folklore Database</authority>
        <idno type="FFDB">NAF019831</idno>
        <availability status="free">
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">CC BY</licence>
          <p>Note that the CC licence only applies to the XML file. Users should also cite the original source of the text.</p>
        </availability>
        <date when="2025">2025</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Turnbull, Colin M. (1959): Legends of the BaMbuti. In: The Journal of the Royal Anthropological Institute of Great Britain and Ireland 89(1), 45-60. Quot. p. 53.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text digitized and encoded for use in the Forager Folklore Database. The FFDB
                    offers a basis for a systematic study of narrative universals, the evolutionary 
                    origin of storytelling, and (comparative) folklore studies.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p>The narrative was selected for being a genuine piece of oral literature recorded
                    directly, or mediated by an interpreter, from a narrator who either lived or
                    grew up as a member of a culture whose subsistence at the time of recording was,
                    or until recently had been, depending primarily on hunting, gathering, and/or
                    fishing. Care was taken to ensure the quality of the recording and the relative
                    absence of external cultural influences.</p>
      </samplingDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          <tagUsage gi="persName">Used to mark personal names (usually characters).</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="placeName">Used to mark place names.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="rs" occurs="18">Referencing strings are used to mark up animal names, plant names, 
                        and colors. The <att>type</att> attribute correspondingly takes one of the following 
                        values:
                        <list type="gloss"><label><val>animal</val></label><item>animal name</item><label><val>plant</val></label><item>plant name</item><label><val>color</val></label><item>color adjective or noun</item></list>
                    </tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="shift" occurs="1">Used to mark shifts towards a metatextual level or back to the 
                        diegesis. The <att>feature</att> attributes takes one of the following values:
                        <list type="gloss"><label><val>anamyth</val></label><item>Shift to a framing metacommentary at the beginning of a narrative.</item><label><val>apartmyth</val></label><item>Shift to a comment or aside within the course of a narration.</item><label><val>epimyth</val></label><item>Shift to a framing metacommentary at the end of a narrative.</item><label><val>diegesis</val></label><item>Shift back to the diegesis of the tale.</item></list>
                    </tagUsage>
        </namespace>
      </tagsDecl>
      <listPrefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="p" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="../references/personography.xml#$1">
          <p>Private URIs using the <code>p</code> prefix are pointers to <gi>person</gi>
                        elements in the <name type="file">personography.xml</name> file.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="q" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/$1">
          <p>URIs using the <code>q</code> prefix are <name ref="q:Q43649390">Wikidata Q
                        identifiers</name> and refer to the respective entries on <orgName ref="https://www.wikidata.org/">Wikidata</orgName>.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="g" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="">
          <!-- write a replacementPattern once glossaries are online -->
          <p>Private URIs using the <code>g</code> prefix are pointers to the respective
                        lemmas in the FFDB collection of glossaries.</p>
        </prefixDef>
      </listPrefixDef>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Footnotes are generally retained, but no effort has been made to link the
                    narratives mentioned in comparative notes with corresponding records within the
                    FFDB.</p>
        <p>Page numbers have been retained, but page beginnings, <gi>pb</gi>, occurring
                    within a word have been moved either before or after the word (or nominal
                    phrase) on a case to case basis, without general rule.</p>
        <normalization method="silent">
          <p>Omissions as well as supplementations by the original editor are set in
                        brackets. In all other cases, parentheses in the original are retained.</p>
          <p>Latin passages in the original (usually to mask language and themes deemed
                        indecent) are rendered in English.</p>
        </normalization>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>End-of-line hyphenation has been removed. All other hyphenation has been
                        retained.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <quotation marks="all">
          <p>All quotation marks have been retained. No effort was made to mark up
                        passages in quotation marks as, for example, <gi>q</gi>, <gi>quote</gi>, <gi>
                        said</gi>, <gi>cit</gi>, or <gi>soCalled</gi>.</p>
        </quotation>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Refer to the <gi>tagsDecl</gi>.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <name type="culture" key="CAF00111">Mbuti-Sua</name>
          <date notAfter="1954" notBefore="1953" type="recorded">Recorded sometime between 1953 and 1954.</date>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p>An <rs type="animal">elephant</rs> and a pygmy were friends. The pygmy was called <persName>Nbali</persName>. He went to visit his friend, the <rs type="animal">elephant</rs>. When he arrived at the <rs type="animal">elephant</rs>'s village the <rs type="animal">elephant</rs> was delighted and said to his wife, "My friend Nbali has come, make us a nice dish of mashed <rs type="plant">plantains</rs>." So his wife pounded the <rs type="plant">plantains</rs>, added the salt, and put the dish over the fire. When it was ready the <rs type="animal">elephant</rs> took some <rs type="color">red</rs>-hot embers and held them to his feet, and the <rs type="animal">elephant</rs> fat ran into the food. When there was enough he turned to his friend, <persName>Nbali</persName>, and said, "Eat well." The two of them sat down and ate up all the food. The pygmy said, "This is delicious". He went back to his camp. The next day the <rs type="animal">elephant</rs> said to his wife, 'Now I will go and visit my pygmy friend, <persName>Nbali</persName>.' So he cleaned himself up and set off. When he arrived at <persName>Nbali</persName>'s camp, <persName>Nbali</persName> saw him and called, 'Welcome, Friend! Come and sit down.' He told his wife that his friend had come, and that she should prepare some mashed <rs type="plant">plantains</rs> for him. His wife prepared the food, and put it on the fire. When it was cooked the pygmy took some <rs type="color">red</rs>-hot embers and started putting them to his foot. The <rs type="animal">elephant</rs> said, "Don't do that, it will kill you. My feet are big and heavy, let me do it." "Don't be silly," replied the pygmy, and put the embers to his feet. He screamed with pain and almost died. The <rs type="animal">elephant</rs> took hold of him and brought him back to life, then said, "See, I told you it would kill you." The <rs type="animal">elephant</rs> then took the hot embers to his feet so that the oil ran out into the <rs type="plant">plantains</rs>, and they all sat down and ate. When the meal was finished the <rs type="animal">elephant</rs> returned to his home. His wife greeted him and asked if he had had a good time. He said, "It was terrible. My friend <persName>Nbali</persName> took <rs type="color">red</rs>-hot embers and put them to his feet and almost killed himself. I shall never go back there again, never." <shift feature="epimyth"/>Basi ['That is all'].</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
