<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Mantis Assumes the Form of a Hartebeest</title>
        <editor ref="p:Bleek79" role="collector">Wilhelm Heinrich Immanuel Bleek</editor>
        <editor ref="p:Kabbo153" role="narrator">ǁKabbo ('dreams')</editor>
        <funder>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</funder>
        <principal>
          <persName>Katja Mellmann</persName>
          <persName>Michelle Scalise Sugiyama</persName>
        </principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>XML template, digitization architecture, and automated inline tagging</resp>
          <persName>Jan Jokisch</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <extent>
        <measure unit="KB" quantity="22">About 22 kilobytes</measure>
      </extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Forager Folklore Database</authority>
        <idno type="FFDB">NAF000356</idno>
        <availability status="free">
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">CC BY</licence>
        </availability>
        <date when="2025">2025</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Bleek, Wilhelm H. I./Lloyd, Lucy C. (1911): Specimens of Bushman Folklore. London: Allen. Quot. pp. 2-17.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text digitized and encoded for use in the Forager Folklore Database. The FFDB
                    offers a basis for a systematic study of narrative universals, the evolutionary 
                    origin of storytelling, and (comparative) folklore studies.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p>The narrative was selected for being a genuine piece of oral literature recorded
                    directly, or mediated by an interpreter, from a narrator who either lived or
                    grew up as a member of a culture whose subsistence at the time of recording was,
                    or until recently had been, depending primarily on hunting, gathering, and/or
                    fishing. Care was taken to ensure the quality of the recording and the relative
                    absence of external cultural influences.</p>
      </samplingDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          <tagUsage gi="persName">Used to mark personal names (usually characters).</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="placeName">Used to mark place names.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="rs" occurs="99">Referencing strings are used to mark up animal names, plant names, 
                        and colors. The <att>type</att> attribute correspondingly takes one of the following 
                        values:
                        <list type="gloss"><label><val>animal</val></label><item>animal name</item><label><val>plant</val></label><item>plant name</item><label><val>color</val></label><item>color adjective or noun</item></list>
                    </tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="shift" occurs="0">Used to mark shifts towards a metatextual level or back to the 
                        diegesis. The <att>feature</att> attributes takes one of the following values:
                        <list type="gloss"><label><val>anamyth</val></label><item>Shift to a framing metacommentary at the beginning of a narrative.</item><label><val>apartmyth</val></label><item>Shift to a comment or aside within the course of a narration.</item><label><val>epimyth</val></label><item>Shift to a framing metacommentary at the end of a narrative.</item><label><val>diegesis</val></label><item>Shift back to the diegesis of the tale.</item></list>
                    </tagUsage>
        </namespace>
      </tagsDecl>
      <listPrefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="p" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="../references/personography.xml#$1">
          <p>Private URIs using the <code>p</code> prefix are pointers to <gi>person</gi>
                        elements in the <name type="file">personography.xml</name> file.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="q" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/$1">
          <p>URIs using the <code>q</code> prefix are <name ref="q:Q43649390">Wikidata Q
                        identifiers</name> and refer to the respective entries on <orgName ref="https://www.wikidata.org/">Wikidata</orgName>.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="g" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="">
          <!-- write a replacementPattern once glossaries are online -->
          <p>Private URIs using the <code>g</code> prefix are pointers to the respective
                        lemmas in the FFDB collection of glossaries.</p>
        </prefixDef>
      </listPrefixDef>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Footnotes are generally retained, but no effort has been made to link the
                    narratives mentioned in comparative notes with corresponding records within the
                    FFDB.</p>
        <p>Page numbers have been retained, but page beginnings, <gi>pb</gi>, occurring
                    within a word have been moved either before or after the word (or nominal
                    phrase) on a case to case basis, without general rule.</p>
        <normalization method="silent">
          <p>Omissions as well as supplementations by the original editor are set in
                        brackets. In all other cases, parentheses in the original are retained.</p>
          <p>Latin passages in the original (usually to mask language and themes deemed
                        indecent) are rendered in English.</p>
        </normalization>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>End-of-line hyphenation has been removed. All other hyphenation has been
                        retained.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <quotation marks="all">
          <p>All quotation marks have been retained. No effort was made to mark up
                        passages in quotation marks as, for example, <gi>q</gi>, <gi>quote</gi>, <gi>
                        said</gi>, <gi>cit</gi>, or <gi>soCalled</gi>.</p>
        </quotation>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Refer to the <gi>tagsDecl</gi>.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <name type="culture" key="CAF00214">ǀXam</name>
          <date notAfter="1873" notBefore="1871" type="recorded">Recorded sometime between 1871 and 1873.</date>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="URLtoOurTMI">
          <!-- link to our TMI once its online -->
          <list>
            <item resp="#KH">
              <idno type="TMI">A521</idno>
              <term>A521. Culture hero as dupe or trickster.</term>
            </item>
            <item resp="#KH">
              <idno type="TMI">D114</idno>
              <term>D114. Transformation: man to ungulate (wild).</term>
            </item>
            <item resp="#KH">
              <idno type="TMI">D114.1.1</idno>
              <term>D114.1.1. Transformation: man to deer. (Cf. B641.2.)</term>
            </item>
            <item resp="#KH">
              <idno type="TMI">D114.1.3</idno>
              <term>D114.1.3. Transformation: man to hartebeest.</term>
            </item>
            <item resp="#KH">
              <idno type="TMI">T471</idno>
              <term>T471. Rape.</term>
            </item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p>The <rs type="animal">Mantis</rs> is one who cheated the children, by becoming a <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>, by resembling a dead-<rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>. He feigning death lay in front of the children, when the children went to seek <rs type="plant">gambroo [ǀkūï, a sort of cucumber]</rs>; because he thought [wished] that the children should cut him up with a stone knife, as these children did not possess metal knives.</p>
      <p>The children perceived him, when he had laid himself stretched out, while his horns were turned backwards. The children then said to each other: "It is a <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs> that yonder lies; it is dead." The children jumped for joy [saying]: "Our <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>! we shall eat great meat." They broke off stone knives by striking [one stone against another],<note>They broke off, by striking with one stone against another</note> they skinned the <rs type="animal">Mantis</rs>. The skin of the <rs type="animal">Mantis</rs> snatched itself quickly out of the children's hands. They say to each other: "Hold thou strongly fast for me the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs> skin!" Another child said: "The <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs> skin pulled at me."</p>
      <p>Her elder sister said: "It does seem that the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs> has not a wound from the people who shot it; for, the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs> appears to have died of itself. Although the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs> is fat, [yet] the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs> has no shooting wound."</p>
      <p>Her elder sister cut off a shoulder of the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>, and put it down [on a <rs type="plant">bush</rs>]. The <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s shoulder arose by itself, it sat down nicely [on the <pb n="5"/>other side of the <rs type="plant">bush</rs>], while it placed itself nicely. She [then] cut off a thigh of the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>, and put it down [on a <rs type="plant">bush</rs>]; it placed itself nicely on the <rs type="plant">bush</rs>. She cut off another shoulder of the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>, and put it upon [another] <rs type="plant">bush</rs>. It arose, and sat upon a soft [portion of the] <rs type="plant">bush</rs>; as it felt that the <rs type="plant">bush</rs> [upon which the child had laid it] pricked it.</p>
      <p>Another elder sister cut off the other thigh of the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>. They spoke thus: "This <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s flesh does move;<note>The children truly thought that the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s flesh moved. The <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s flesh seemed as if it was not <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>; for, the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s flesh was like a man's flesh, it moved. | [As regards] a man's flesh, when another man shoots him, the poison enters the body. The people cutting break away his flesh, while they cutting take away the mouth of the poisonous wound. The people set aside the man's flesh; it remains quivering, while the other part of the flesh moves [quivers] in his body, - that [flesh] which he sits in [literally 'which he possesses sitting'], that which the people cutting broke. This it is which moves in the [cut out] wound's mouth, while the flesh feels that the flesh is warm. Therefore, the flesh moves, as [while] the flesh [feels that the flesh] is alive; hence it is warm. As [while] the man [feels that he] warms himself at the fire, all his flesh is warm, while it [feels that it] lives. The thing [reason] on account of which he really dies is that his flesh feels cool. While it feels that it is cold, his flesh becomes very cold. This is the reason why his flesh dies.</note> that must be why it shrinks away."</p>
      <p>They arrange their burdens; one says to the other: "Cut and break off the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s neck, so that [thy] younger sister may carry the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s head, for, [thy] yonder sitting elder sister, she shall carry the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s back, she who is a big girl. For, we must carrying return [home]; for, we came [and] cut up this <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>. Its flesh moves; <pb n="7"/>its flesh snatches itself out of our hand. ǀáttāǃ<note>This seems to be an exclamation, the meaning of which is not yet known to the editor.</note> it of itself places itself nicely."</p>
      <p>They take up the flesh of the <rs type="animal">Mantis</rs>; they say to the child: "Carry the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s head, that father may put it to roast for you." The child slung on the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s head, she called to her sisters "Taking hold help me up;<note>The child lay upon her back upon the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s head.</note> this <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s head is not light." Her sisters taking hold of her help her up.</p>
      <p>They go away, they return [home]. The <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s head slips downwards, because the <rs type="animal">Mantis</rs>'s head wishes to stand on the ground. The child lifts it up [with her shoulders], the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s head [by turning a little] removes the thong from the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s eye. The <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s head was whispering, it whispering said to the child: "O child! the thong is standing in front of my eye. Take away for me the thong; the thong is shutting my eye." The child looked behind her; the <rs type="animal">Mantis</rs> winked at the child. The child whimpered; her elder sister looked back at her. Her elder sister called to her: "Come forward quickly; we return [home]."</p>
      <p>The child exclaimed: "This <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s head is able to speak." Her elder sister scolded her: "Lying come forward; we go. Art thou not coming deceiving [us] about the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s head?"</p>
      <p>The child said to her elder sister: "The hartebeest has winked at me with the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s eye; the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs> desired that I should take away the thong <pb n="9"/>from his eye. Thus it was that the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s head lay looking behind my back."</p>
      <p>The child looked back at the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s head, the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs> opened and shut its eyes. The child said to her elder sister: "The <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s head must be alive, for it is opening and shutting its eyes."</p>
      <p>The child, walking on, unloosened the thong; the child let fall the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s head. The <rs type="animal">Mantis</rs> scolded the child, he complained about his head. He scolded the child: "Oh! oh! my head!<note>He was merely complaining about his head.</note> Oh! bad little person!<note>Mantis pronunciation of ǀnúǃkuíʘụa wwé. The cursing of the Flat Bushmen. When a Flat Bushman is angry with another, then it is that he is wont to say ǀnúǃkuí, resembling ǀnússaǃé [the name by which the Flat Bushmen call the Grass Bushmen], for the other one's name. When he loves another person he is wont to say 'mate'; he is wont to say 'brother' when they love each other.</note> hurting me in my head."</p>
      <p>Her sisters let fall the flesh of the <rs type="animal">Mantis</rs>. The flesh of the <rs type="animal">Mantis</rs> sprang together, it quickly joined itself to the lower part of the <rs type="animal">Mantis</rs>'s back. The head of the <rs type="animal">Mantis</rs> quickly joined [itself] upon the top of the neck of the <rs type="animal">Mantis</rs>. The neck of the <rs type="animal">Mantis</rs> quickly joined [itself] upon the upper part of the <rs type="animal">Mantis</rs>'s spine. The upper part of the <rs type="animal">Mantis</rs>'s spine joined itself to the <rs type="animal">Mantis</rs>'s back. The thigh of the <rs type="animal">Mantis</rs> sprang forward,<note>The <rs type="animal">Mantis</rs>'s thigh sprang forward like a frog.</note> it joined itself to the <rs type="animal">Mantis</rs>'s back. His other thigh ran forward, racing it joined itself to the other side of the <rs type="animal">Mantis</rs>'s back. The chest of the <rs type="animal">Mantis</rs> ran forward, it joined itself to the front side of the upper part of the <rs type="animal">Mantis</rs>'s spine. The shoulder blade of the <rs type="animal">Mantis</rs> ran forward, it joined itself on to the ribs of the <rs type="animal">Mantis</rs>. <pb n="11"/>The other shoulder blade of the <rs type="animal">Mantis</rs> ran forward, while it felt that the ribs of the <rs type="animal">Mantis</rs> had joined themselves on, when they raced.</p>
      <p>The children still ran on; he [the <rs type="animal">Mantis</rs>, arose from the ground and] ran, while he chased the children, - he being whole, - his head being round, - while he felt that he was a man.<note>He became a man while he was putting himself together again.</note> Therefore, he was stepping along with [his] shoes, while he jogged with his shoulder blade.<note>With his left shoulder blade, he being a left-handed man.</note></p>
      <p>He saw that the children had reached home; he quickly turned about, he, jogging with his shoulder blade, descended to the river. He went along the river bed, making a noise as he stepped in the soft sand; he yonder went quickly out of the river bed. He returned, coming out at a different side of the house [i.e. his own house] he returned, passing in front of the house.</p>
      <p>The children said: "We have been [and] seen a <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs> which was dead. That <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>, it was the one which we cut up with stone knives; its flesh quivered. The <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s flesh quickly snatched itself out of our hands. It by itself was placing itself nicely upon <rs type="plant">bushes</rs> which were comfortable; while the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs> felt that the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s head would go along whispering. While the child who sits [there] carried it, it talking stood behind the child's back."</p>
      <p>The child said to her father "O papa! Dost thou seem to think that the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s head did not talk to me? For the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s head felt that it would be looking at my hole above the nape of the <pb n="13"/>neck, as I went along; and then it was that the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s head told me that I should take away for him the thong from his eye. For, the thong lay in front of his eye."</p>
      <p>Her father said to them: "Have you been and cut up the old man, the <rs type="animal">Mantis</rs>, while he lay pretending to be dead in front of you?"</p>
      <p>The children said: "We thought that the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s horns were there, the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs> had hair. The hartebeest was one which had not an arrow's wound; while the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs> felt that the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs> would talk. Therefore, the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs> came and chased us, when we had put down the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s flesh. The <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s flesh jumped together, while it springing gathered [itself] together, that it might mend, that it might mending hold together to the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s back. The <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s back also joined on.</p>
      <p>Therefore, the hartebeest ran forward, while his body was <rs type="color">red</rs>, when he had no hair [that coat of hair in which he had been lying down], as he ran, swinging his arm like a man.</p>
      <p>And when he saw that we reached the house, he whisked round, He ran, kicking up his heels [showing the <rs type="color">white</rs> soles of his shoes], while he running went before the wind, while the sun shone upon his feet's face [soles], while he ran with all his might into the little river [bed], that he might pass behind the back of the hill lying yonder."</p>
      <p>Their parents said to the children: "You are those who went and cut up the old man 'Tinderbox Owner.' He, there behind, was one who gently came out from the place there behind."</p>
      <p>The children said to their fathers: "He has <pb n="15"/>gone round, he ran fast. He always seems as if he would come over the little hill lying yonder when he sees that we are just reaching home.</p>
      <p>While this little daughter, she was the one to whom the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s head, going along, talked; and then she told us. Therefore, we let fall the <rs type="animal">hartebeest</rs>'s flesh; we laid our karosses on our shoulders, that we might run very fast.</p>
      <p>While its flesh running came together on its back, it finished mending itself. He arose and ran forward, he, quickly moving his arms, chased us. Therefore, we did thus, we became tired from it, on account of the running with which he had chased us, while he did verily move his arms fast.</p>
      <p>Then he descended into the small river, - while he thought that he would, moving his arms fast, run along the small river. Then he thus did, he, picking up wood, came out; while we sat, feeling the fatigue; because he had been deceiving. While he felt that all the people saw him, when we came carrying his thighs, when he went to die lying in front of us; while he wished that we should feel this fatigue, while this child here, it carried his head, - he looked up with fixed eyes. He was as if he was dead; he was [afterwards] opening and shutting his eyes; he afar lay talking [while the children were running off]. He talked while he mended his body; his head talked, while he mended his body. His head talking reached his back; it came to join upon the top [of his neck].</p>
      <p>He ran forward; he yonder will sit deceiving, [at home], while we did cut him up with stone knives [splinters]. ǀá-ttāǃ he went feigning death to lie in front of us, that we might do so, we run.</p>
      <p><pb n="17"/>This fatigue, it is that which we are feeling; and our hearts burnt on account of it. Therefore, we shall not hunt [for food], for we shall altogether remain at home."</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
