<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Creation of the First Human Beings</title>
        <editor ref="p:Howell48" role="collector">Signe Howell</editor>
        <editor ref="p:unidentified0" role="narrator">unidentified</editor>
        <funder>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</funder>
        <principal>
          <persName>Katja Mellmann</persName>
          <persName>Michelle Scalise Sugiyama</persName>
        </principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>XML template, digitization architecture, and automated inline tagging</resp>
          <persName>Jan Jokisch</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <extent>
        <measure unit="KB" quantity="11">About 11 kilobytes</measure>
      </extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Forager Folklore Database</authority>
        <idno type="FFDB">NEE020446</idno>
        <availability status="free">
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">CC BY</licence>
          <p>Note that the CC licence only applies to the XML file. Users should also cite the original source of the text.</p>
        </availability>
        <date when="2025">2025</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Howell, Signe (1982): Chewong Myths and Legends. Kuala Lumpur: Art Printing Works (The Malaysian Branch of the Royal Asiatic Society Monographs, 11). Quot. p. 2.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text digitized and encoded for use in the Forager Folklore Database. The FFDB
                    offers a basis for a systematic study of narrative universals, the evolutionary 
                    origin of storytelling, and (comparative) folklore studies.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p>The narrative was selected for being a genuine piece of oral literature recorded
                    directly, or mediated by an interpreter, from a narrator who either lived or
                    grew up as a member of a culture whose subsistence at the time of recording was,
                    or until recently had been, depending primarily on hunting, gathering, and/or
                    fishing. Care was taken to ensure the quality of the recording and the relative
                    absence of external cultural influences.</p>
      </samplingDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          <tagUsage gi="persName">Used to mark personal names (usually characters).</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="placeName">Used to mark place names.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="rs" occurs="2">Referencing strings are used to mark up animal names, plant names, 
                        and colors. The <att>type</att> attribute correspondingly takes one of the following 
                        values:
                        <list type="gloss"><label><val>animal</val></label><item>animal name</item><label><val>plant</val></label><item>plant name</item><label><val>color</val></label><item>color adjective or noun</item></list>
                    </tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="shift" occurs="0">Used to mark shifts towards a metatextual level or back to the 
                        diegesis. The <att>feature</att> attributes takes one of the following values:
                        <list type="gloss"><label><val>anamyth</val></label><item>Shift to a framing metacommentary at the beginning of a narrative.</item><label><val>apartmyth</val></label><item>Shift to a comment or aside within the course of a narration.</item><label><val>epimyth</val></label><item>Shift to a framing metacommentary at the end of a narrative.</item><label><val>diegesis</val></label><item>Shift back to the diegesis of the tale.</item></list>
                    </tagUsage>
        </namespace>
      </tagsDecl>
      <listPrefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="p" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="../references/personography.xml#$1">
          <p>Private URIs using the <code>p</code> prefix are pointers to <gi>person</gi>
                        elements in the <name type="file">personography.xml</name> file.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="q" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/$1">
          <p>URIs using the <code>q</code> prefix are <name ref="q:Q43649390">Wikidata Q
                        identifiers</name> and refer to the respective entries on <orgName ref="https://www.wikidata.org/">Wikidata</orgName>.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="g" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="">
          <!-- write a replacementPattern once glossaries are online -->
          <p>Private URIs using the <code>g</code> prefix are pointers to the respective
                        lemmas in the FFDB collection of glossaries.</p>
        </prefixDef>
      </listPrefixDef>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Footnotes are generally retained, but no effort has been made to link the
                    narratives mentioned in comparative notes with corresponding records within the
                    FFDB.</p>
        <p>Page numbers have been retained, but page beginnings, <gi>pb</gi>, occurring
                    within a word have been moved either before or after the word (or nominal
                    phrase) on a case to case basis, without general rule.</p>
        <normalization method="silent">
          <p>Omissions as well as supplementations by the original editor are set in
                        brackets. In all other cases, parentheses in the original are retained.</p>
          <p>Latin passages in the original (usually to mask language and themes deemed
                        indecent) are rendered in English.</p>
        </normalization>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>End-of-line hyphenation has been removed. All other hyphenation has been
                        retained.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <quotation marks="all">
          <p>All quotation marks have been retained. No effort was made to mark up
                        passages in quotation marks as, for example, <gi>q</gi>, <gi>quote</gi>, <gi>
                        said</gi>, <gi>cit</gi>, or <gi>soCalled</gi>.</p>
        </quotation>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Refer to the <gi>tagsDecl</gi>.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <name type="culture" key="CEE20501">Chewong</name>
          <date notAfter="1979" notBefore="1977" type="recorded">Recorded sometime between 1977 and 1979.</date>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="URLtoOurTMI">
          <!-- link to our TMI once its online -->
          <list>
            <item resp="#FFDB">
              <idno type="TMI">A1200</idno>
              <term>A1200. Creation of man.</term>
            </item>
            <item resp="#FFDB">
              <idno type="TMI">A1212</idno>
              <term>A1212. Man created in creator's image.</term>
            </item>
            <item resp="#FFDB">
              <idno type="TMI">A1270</idno>
              <term>A1270. Primeval human pair.</term>
            </item>
            <item resp="#FFDB">
              <idno type="TMI">A1271</idno>
              <term>A1271. Origin of first parents.</term>
            </item>
            <item resp="#FFDB">
              <idno type="TMI">A1277</idno>
              <term>A1277. Offspring of first parents.</term>
            </item>
            <item resp="#FFDB">
              <idno type="TMI">A1352</idno>
              <term>A1352. Origin of sexual intercourse.</term>
            </item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p>A long, long time ago there were no people on Earth Seven. <persName>Allah TaʼAllah</persName><note><persName>Allah TaʼAllah</persName> is from the Arabic meaning God Most High. The term is also used by the Muslim Malays.</note> [sometimes referred to as Tohan<note>Tohan is from the Malay Tuhan which is the common name for God.</note>] told his Nabi<note>Nabi is the Malay word for prophet, usually referring to Mohammad when it is spelt with capital "n". These three names are clearly borrowed form the Muslim Malays, and are a means by which the Chewong show the outside world that they, contrary to popular Malay belief, also have a religion and tradition (adal). The Chewong are always insistent that their Tohan etc. are not the same as that of the Malays. It is impossible to estimate when these names were introduced into the Chewong cosmology</note> to make people out of earth. The Nabi did not know what people were supposed to look like, so he first made the shape of an <rs type="animal">elephant</rs>. When <persName>Allah TaʼAllah</persName> saw it he said, "That is not people (beri) that is an <rs type="animal">elephant</rs>; make them so they look like us. So the Nabi tried again and this time he made the shape of a human being. He made two shapes, one man and one woman, but they were not alive. So he went to <persName>Allah TaʼAllah</persName> and told him that the figures had no breath (njug). <persName>Allah TaʼAllah</persName> blew into his clenched fist and passed the breath into Nabi's hands. He had one breath in each hand. He started back to the two earth figures, but on the way he wanted to see what breath looked like, so he opened both fists. He could see nothing, however, and breath disappeared. Nabi returned to <persName>Allah TaʼAllah</persName> who gave him two new breaths<note>See also "How Bas were Made" in Part III.</note>. He went to the figures without looking at the breath, and he placed his fist on the fontanelle of each figure in turn and blew through it. Then he hit their big toes. The two figures stood up. They were alive. They were the first human couple. They did not know what to do in order to have children. The Nabi did not know either. He tried putting a piece of firewood up the anus of the woman, but that was no good. The couple had sexual intercourse, but they did not know what this would lead to. They were stupid. The woman became pregnant, but they did not know, and when she began to have terrible stomach pains they did not understand that she was about to give birth. They did not know what to do, so the man cut open the woman's stomach and took out the child inside. The child lived, but the woman died. This is how the early people delivered their babies. There were no adult women in those days. When their first child was born their husbands cut open their stomachs and the women died. The husband did not know what to do with the child, but his wife's ghost (yinlugen) came to him in a dream and told him to let the child suck at his elbow. The man did this, and milk appeared which the child drank. This was how all babies were kept alive after their mothers had died.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
