<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>How Tigers Came to Eat Humans</title>
        <editor ref="p:Howell48" role="collector">Signe Howell</editor>
        <editor ref="p:unidentified0" role="narrator">unidentified</editor>
        <funder>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</funder>
        <principal>
          <persName>Katja Mellmann</persName>
          <persName>Michelle Scalise Sugiyama</persName>
        </principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>XML template, digitization architecture, and automated inline tagging</resp>
          <persName>Jan Jokisch</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <extent>
        <measure unit="KB" quantity="9">About 9 kilobytes</measure>
      </extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Forager Folklore Database</authority>
        <idno type="FFDB">NEE023308</idno>
        <availability status="free">
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">CC BY</licence>
          <p>Note that the CC licence only applies to the XML file. Users should also cite the original source of the text.</p>
        </availability>
        <date when="2025">2025</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Howell, Signe (1982): Chewong Myths and Legends. Kuala Lumpur: Art Printing Works (The Malaysian Branch of the Royal Asiatic Society Monographs, 11). Quot. p. 10.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text digitized and encoded for use in the Forager Folklore Database. The FFDB
                    offers a basis for a systematic study of narrative universals, the evolutionary 
                    origin of storytelling, and (comparative) folklore studies.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p>The narrative was selected for being a genuine piece of oral literature recorded
                    directly, or mediated by an interpreter, from a narrator who either lived or
                    grew up as a member of a culture whose subsistence at the time of recording was,
                    or until recently had been, depending primarily on hunting, gathering, and/or
                    fishing. Care was taken to ensure the quality of the recording and the relative
                    absence of external cultural influences.</p>
      </samplingDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          <tagUsage gi="persName">Used to mark personal names (usually characters).</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="placeName">Used to mark place names.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="rs" occurs="22">Referencing strings are used to mark up animal names, plant names, 
                        and colors. The <att>type</att> attribute correspondingly takes one of the following 
                        values:
                        <list type="gloss"><label><val>animal</val></label><item>animal name</item><label><val>plant</val></label><item>plant name</item><label><val>color</val></label><item>color adjective or noun</item></list>
                    </tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="shift" occurs="1">Used to mark shifts towards a metatextual level or back to the 
                        diegesis. The <att>feature</att> attributes takes one of the following values:
                        <list type="gloss"><label><val>anamyth</val></label><item>Shift to a framing metacommentary at the beginning of a narrative.</item><label><val>apartmyth</val></label><item>Shift to a comment or aside within the course of a narration.</item><label><val>epimyth</val></label><item>Shift to a framing metacommentary at the end of a narrative.</item><label><val>diegesis</val></label><item>Shift back to the diegesis of the tale.</item></list>
                    </tagUsage>
        </namespace>
      </tagsDecl>
      <listPrefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="p" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="../references/personography.xml#$1">
          <p>Private URIs using the <code>p</code> prefix are pointers to <gi>person</gi>
                        elements in the <name type="file">personography.xml</name> file.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="q" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/$1">
          <p>URIs using the <code>q</code> prefix are <name ref="q:Q43649390">Wikidata Q
                        identifiers</name> and refer to the respective entries on <orgName ref="https://www.wikidata.org/">Wikidata</orgName>.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="g" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="">
          <!-- write a replacementPattern once glossaries are online -->
          <p>Private URIs using the <code>g</code> prefix are pointers to the respective
                        lemmas in the FFDB collection of glossaries.</p>
        </prefixDef>
      </listPrefixDef>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Footnotes are generally retained, but no effort has been made to link the
                    narratives mentioned in comparative notes with corresponding records within the
                    FFDB.</p>
        <p>Page numbers have been retained, but page beginnings, <gi>pb</gi>, occurring
                    within a word have been moved either before or after the word (or nominal
                    phrase) on a case to case basis, without general rule.</p>
        <normalization method="silent">
          <p>Omissions as well as supplementations by the original editor are set in
                        brackets. In all other cases, parentheses in the original are retained.</p>
          <p>Latin passages in the original (usually to mask language and themes deemed
                        indecent) are rendered in English.</p>
        </normalization>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>End-of-line hyphenation has been removed. All other hyphenation has been
                        retained.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <quotation marks="all">
          <p>All quotation marks have been retained. No effort was made to mark up
                        passages in quotation marks as, for example, <gi>q</gi>, <gi>quote</gi>, <gi>
                        said</gi>, <gi>cit</gi>, or <gi>soCalled</gi>.</p>
        </quotation>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Refer to the <gi>tagsDecl</gi>.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <name type="culture" key="CEE20501">Chewong</name>
          <date notAfter="1979" notBefore="1977" type="recorded">Recorded sometime between 1977 and 1979.</date>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="URLtoOurTMI">
          <!-- link to our TMI once its online -->
          <list>
            <item resp="#FFDB">
              <idno type="TMI">A2435.3.9.3</idno>
              <term>A2435.3.9.3. Why tigers eat human flesh.</term>
            </item>
            <item resp="#FFDB">
              <idno type="TMI">B431.3</idno>
              <term>B431.3. Helpful tiger.</term>
            </item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p>In the old days <rs type="animal">Tiger</rs> did not eat human beings. She would go to places where people lived and take a small child and bring it to her own house where she would look after it and rear it. When the child became old it would return to its mother and father, and <rs type="animal">Tiger</rs> would take another small child instead and bring it up. Each time the child had grown up, however, <rs type="animal">Tiger</rs> would let it go home. People did not mind letting <rs type="animal">Tiger</rs> have the children, they knew that she would look after them well.</p>
      <p>Then one day as <rs type="animal">Tiger</rs> was carrying a new child back to her house, she met a <rs type="animal">toad</rs> who asked her what she was doing. "I am bringing my new child home," replied <rs type="animal">Tiger</rs>. "That is not your child, that is our meat (<rs ref="g:GEE2143.002">ai</rs>)" said the <rs type="animal">toad</rs>. "No, no," said <rs type="animal">Tiger</rs>, "It is my child. I look after it." "It is very good to eat," the <rs type="animal">toad</rs> told her, "We'll eat it together". "No, no, it is my child," insisted <rs type="animal">Tiger</rs>. But the <rs type="animal">toad</rs> took the child and struck it so hard that it died. Then she cut it up into little pieces, put them in a <rs type="plant">bamboo</rs> and cooked it. When it was cooked she gave some meat to the <rs type="animal">tiger</rs>. "Try a little, it is very good," she told the <rs type="animal">tiger</rs> who then tasted just a tiny bit. "Oh, it is very good!" exclaimed <rs type="animal">Tiger</rs>, and together the <rs type="animal">toad</rs> and <rs type="animal">Tiger</rs> finished eating the child. Once having got the taste for human flesh, <rs type="animal">Tiger</rs> wanted more, and she killed and ate the next human child she took. When people found out that <rs type="animal">Tiger</rs> was eating their children, they no longer gave away their children to her. <shift feature="epimyth"/>From then on <rs type="animal">tigers</rs> have been hunting humans.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
