<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Q!āʼnēqēᵋlakᵘ and Xatēʼtsᴇn</title>
        <editor ref="p:Boas15" role="collector">Franz Boas</editor>
        <editor ref="p:Wanukᵘ1000" role="narrator">Waʼnukᵘ</editor>
        <funder>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</funder>
        <principal>
          <persName>Katja Mellmann</persName>
          <persName>Michelle Scalise Sugiyama</persName>
        </principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>XML template, digitization architecture, and automated inline tagging</resp>
          <persName>Jan Jokisch</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <extent>
        <measure unit="KB" quantity="12">About 12 kilobytes</measure>
      </extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Forager Folklore Database</authority>
        <idno type="FFDB">NNA019448</idno>
        <availability status="free">
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">CC BY</licence>
        </availability>
        <date when="2025">2025</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Boas, Franz (1910): Kwakiutl Tales. New York: Columbia University Press &amp; Leyden: Brill (Columbia University Contributions to Anthropology, 2). Quot. pp. 2-7.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text digitized and encoded for use in the Forager Folklore Database. The FFDB
                    offers a basis for a systematic study of narrative universals, the evolutionary 
                    origin of storytelling, and (comparative) folklore studies.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p>The narrative was selected for being a genuine piece of oral literature recorded
                    directly, or mediated by an interpreter, from a narrator who either lived or
                    grew up as a member of a culture whose subsistence at the time of recording was,
                    or until recently had been, depending primarily on hunting, gathering, and/or
                    fishing. Care was taken to ensure the quality of the recording and the relative
                    absence of external cultural influences.</p>
      </samplingDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          <tagUsage gi="persName">Used to mark personal names (usually characters).</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="placeName">Used to mark place names.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="rs" occurs="8">Referencing strings are used to mark up animal names, plant names, 
                        and colors. The <att>type</att> attribute correspondingly takes one of the following 
                        values:
                        <list type="gloss"><label><val>animal</val></label><item>animal name</item><label><val>plant</val></label><item>plant name</item><label><val>color</val></label><item>color adjective or noun</item></list>
                    </tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="shift" occurs="0">Used to mark shifts towards a metatextual level or back to the 
                        diegesis. The <att>feature</att> attributes takes one of the following values:
                        <list type="gloss"><label><val>anamyth</val></label><item>Shift to a framing metacommentary at the beginning of a narrative.</item><label><val>apartmyth</val></label><item>Shift to a comment or aside within the course of a narration.</item><label><val>epimyth</val></label><item>Shift to a framing metacommentary at the end of a narrative.</item><label><val>diegesis</val></label><item>Shift back to the diegesis of the tale.</item></list>
                    </tagUsage>
        </namespace>
      </tagsDecl>
      <listPrefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="p" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="../references/personography.xml#$1">
          <p>Private URIs using the <code>p</code> prefix are pointers to <gi>person</gi>
                        elements in the <name type="file">personography.xml</name> file.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="q" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/$1">
          <p>URIs using the <code>q</code> prefix are <name ref="q:Q43649390">Wikidata Q
                        identifiers</name> and refer to the respective entries on <orgName ref="https://www.wikidata.org/">Wikidata</orgName>.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="g" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="">
          <!-- write a replacementPattern once glossaries are online -->
          <p>Private URIs using the <code>g</code> prefix are pointers to the respective
                        lemmas in the FFDB collection of glossaries.</p>
        </prefixDef>
      </listPrefixDef>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Footnotes are generally retained, but no effort has been made to link the
                    narratives mentioned in comparative notes with corresponding records within the
                    FFDB.</p>
        <p>Page numbers have been retained, but page beginnings, <gi>pb</gi>, occurring
                    within a word have been moved either before or after the word (or nominal
                    phrase) on a case to case basis, without general rule.</p>
        <normalization method="silent">
          <p>Omissions as well as supplementations by the original editor are set in
                        brackets. In all other cases, parentheses in the original are retained.</p>
          <p>Latin passages in the original (usually to mask language and themes deemed
                        indecent) are rendered in English.</p>
        </normalization>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>End-of-line hyphenation has been removed. All other hyphenation has been
                        retained.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <quotation marks="all">
          <p>All quotation marks have been retained. No effort was made to mark up
                        passages in quotation marks as, for example, <gi>q</gi>, <gi>quote</gi>, <gi>
                        said</gi>, <gi>cit</gi>, or <gi>soCalled</gi>.</p>
        </quotation>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Refer to the <gi>tagsDecl</gi>.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <name type="culture" key="CNA29001">Kwakwakaʼwakw</name>
          <date when="1893" type="recorded">Recorded in 1893.</date>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p><persName>Xatēʼtsᴇn</persName> was sitting in his house when his attendant came and said, "Don't sit here in the house, for somebody is coming to the beach here." - "Maybe this is what I am expecting, that will make things right on the beach." Then <persName>Xatēʼtsᴇn</persName> went out of his house to invite <persName>Q!āʼnēqēᵋlakᵘ</persName>. Then [<persName>Q!āʼnēqēᵋlakᵘ</persName>] entered the house of <persName>Xatēʼtsᴇn</persName>, and he was given dried [<rs type="animal">salmon</rs> to eat. It was dried] meat of the double-headed <rs type="animal">serpent</rs>. <persName>Q!āʼnēqēᵋlakᵘ</persName> began to eat it, and his body became contorted. Then <persName>Xatēʼtsᴇn</persName> spoke. "Don't urge our friend here [to eat]." Then <persName>Xatēʼtsᴇn</persName> and <persName>Q!āʼnēqēᵋlakᵘ</persName> went out of the house. <persName>Xatēʼtsᴇn</persName> looked at his salmon-weir. Then <persName>Q!āʼnēqēᵋlakᵘ</persName> transformed him into stone. <persName>Xatēʼtsᴇn</persName> became a man again, because he also had supernatural power. [He said,] "Go on, take warning, friend! Now I will also do something to you." Then <persName>Xatēʼtsᴇn</persName> transformed his friend into stone, but <persName>Q!āʼnēqēᵋlakᵘ</persName> became a man again.</p>
      <p>Then he warned <persName>Xatēʼtsᴇn</persName>. "Take warning, friend! Now I will try you again." They took hold of each other, and <persName>Q!āʼnēqēᵋlakᵘ</persName> held <persName>Xatēʼtsᴇn</persName> by his sides. He lifted him up. Then <persName>Xatēʼtsᴇn</persName> was transformed into fog. He became a man again. Then <persName>Xatēʼtsᴇn</persName> spoke. "Go on, take warning, friend! Now I will do something to you also." Then <persName>Xatēʼtsᴇn</persName> lifted <persName>Q!āʼnēqēᵋlakᵘ</persName> and threw him upward. Then <persName>Q!āʼnēqēᵋlakᵘ</persName> also became fog. <persName>Q!āʼnēqēᵋlakᵘ</persName> became a man again.</p>
      <p><pb n="5"/>Then <persName>Q!āʼnēqēᵋlakᵘ</persName> spoke. "Go on, take warning, friend! Now I will try to lift you from the rock." Then <persName>Q!āʼnēqēᵋlakᵘ</persName> took hold of <persName>Xatēʼtsᴇn</persName> and threw him upward. He transformed <persName>Xatēʼtsᴇn</persName> into a <rs type="animal">crane</rs>, and the <rs type="animal">crane</rs> began to fly. <persName>Xatēʼtsᴇn</persName> became a man again. Then he also warned <persName>Q!āʼnēqēᵋlakᵘ</persName>. "Go on, take care, friend!" Then <persName>Xatēʼtsᴇn</persName> took hold of <persName>Q!āʼnēqēᵋlakᵘ</persName> and threw him upward. A <rs type="animal">crane</rs> was flying there. <persName>Q!āʼnēqēᵋlakᵘ</persName> became a man again.</p>
      <p>Then <persName>Xatēʼtsᴇn</persName> spoke. "Oh, indeed, you have supernatural power, friend! Come, let us go to my playground." Then they went aboard his canoe, and they paddled, going to <persName>Xatēʼtsᴇn</persName>'s play-round. They were dressed quite with the same kind of belts; namely, double-headed <rs type="animal">serpents</rs>. Double-headed <rs type="animal">serpents</rs> also were their canoes. Then they arrived at the playground.</p>
      <p>Then <persName>Xatēʼtsᴇn</persName> spoke. "Take care, friend! else you might have a mishap on my playground. Nobody who ever tried to come and play on it has succeeded a single time. This is what makes it slippery, the blood of those who came from time to time to play here." Then <persName>Xatēʼtsᴇn</persName> spoke. "You go on first, friend!" Thus <persName>Q!āʼnēqēᵋlakᵘ</persName> was told by his friend. "[No,] you first," said <persName>Q!āʼnēqēᵋlakᵘ</persName>. "You said that it is your playground." - "Let me go first, friend," said <persName>Xatēʼtsᴇn</persName>, on his part. Then he [<persName>Q!āʼnēqēᵋlakᵘ</persName>] clapped on the gunwale of his canoe with his paddle, and <persName>Xatēʼtsᴇn</persName> ran up. <persName>Xatēʼtsᴇn</persName> ran straight up. He did not rest on his resting-place halfway up: he just turned round and came down again and jumped into his canoe.</p>
      <p>Then <persName>Xatēʼtsᴇn</persName> spoke. "Now you go, friend!" Thus he said to <persName>Q!āʼnēqēᵋlakᵘ</persName>. "Take care, fasten your belt well, else it might [drag] behind you!" Then <persName>Q!āʼnēqēᵋlakᵘ</persName> ran. He had nearly reached the top when he <pb n="7"/>slipped on the rock. His belt came off, and <persName>Q!āʼnēqēᵋlakᵘ</persName> fell down. He fell into the water and sank. Then <persName>Xatēʼtsᴇn</persName> went away to <persName>Q!āʼnēqēᵋlakᵘ</persName>'s canoe, and upset it on the water. "Indeed, you have no real supernatural power, friend," thus he said while upsetting <persName>Q!āʼnēqēᵋlakᵘ</persName>'s canoe.</p>
      <p><persName>Xatēʼtsᴇn</persName> waited in vain for <persName>Q!āʼnēqēᵋlakᵘ</persName> to show himself, but <persName>Q!āʼnēqēᵋlakᵘ</persName> just did mischief to <persName>Xatēʼtsᴇn</persName>'s land. <persName>Q!āʼnēqēᵋlakᵘ</persName> transformed into stone a <rs type="animal">beaver</rs> that was sitting by the river. Then <persName>Q!āʼnēqēᵋlakᵘ</persName> caught sight of the watchman at the salmon-weir of <persName>Xatēʼtsᴇn</persName>. He transformed into stone him and his pole. Then he also transformed into stone the watchman of <persName>Xatēʼtsᴇn</persName>. Then <persName>Xatēʼtsᴇn</persName> was vanquished by <persName>Q!āʼnēqēᵋlakᵘ</persName>, for <persName>Xatēʼtsᴇn</persName> did not know what <persName>Q!āʼnēqēᵋlakᵘ</persName> was doing.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
