<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB/main/schema/FFDB.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB/main/schema/FFDB.rng" type="application/xml" 
    schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Old Man of Nutchek</title>
        <editor ref="p:Lavrischeff3931" role="collector">Tikhon I. Lavrischeff</editor>
        <editor ref="p:unidentified0" role="informant">unidentified</editor>
        <funder>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</funder>
        <principal>
          <persName>Katja Mellmann</persName>
          <persName>Michelle Scalise Sugiyama</persName>
        </principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>XML templates, digitization architecture, and automated inline tagging</resp>
          <persName>Jan Jokisch</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <extent>
        <measure unit="KB" quantity="10">About 10 kilobytes</measure>
      </extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Forager Folklore Database</authority>
        <idno type="FFDB">NNA037588</idno>
        <availability status="free">
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/">public domain</licence>
        </availability>
        <date when="2023">2023</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Lavrischeff, T. I. (1928): Two Aleut Tales. In: American Anthropologist NS 30(1), 121-124. Quot. pp. 122-124.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text digitized and encoded for use in the Forager Folklore Database. The FFDB
                    offers a basis for a systematic study of narrative universals,
                    the evolutionary origin of storytelling, and (comparative) folklore studies.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p>The narrative was selected for being a genuine piece of oral literature recorded
                    directly, or mediated by an interpreter, from an informant who either lived or
                    grew up as a member of a culture whose subsistence at the time of recording was,
                    or until recently had been, depending primarily on hunting, gathering, and/or
                    fishing. Care was taken to ensure the quality of the recording and the relative
                    absence of external cultural influences.</p>
      </samplingDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <namespace name="">
          <tagUsage gi="animal" occurs="17">Used to mark animal names mentioned in the text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="plant" occurs="2">Used to mark plant names mentioned in the text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="color" occurs="2">Used to mark colors (adjectives and nouns) mentioned in the
                        text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="persName" occurs="10">Used to mark personal names (usually characters)
                        mentioned in the text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="placeName" occurs="2">Used to mark named place names mentioned in the text.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="anamyth" occurs="0">Used to mark a framing metacommentary at the beginning of
                        a narrative.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="apartmyth" occurs="0">Used to mark comments or asides within the course of a
                        narrative.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="epimyth" occurs="0">Used to mark a framing metacommentary at the end of a
                        narrative.</tagUsage>
        </namespace>
      </tagsDecl>
      <listPrefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="p" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="../references/personography.xml#$1">
          <p>Private URIs using the <code>p</code> prefix are pointers to <gi>person</gi>
                        elements in the <name type="file">personography.xml</name> file.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="q" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/$1">
          <p>URIs using the <code>q</code> prefix are <name ref="q:Q43649390">Wikidata Q
                        identifiers</name> and refer to the respective entries on <orgName ref="https://www.wikidata.org/">Wikidata</orgName>.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="g" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="">
          <!-- write a replacementPattern once glossaries are online -->
          <p>Private URIs using the <code>g</code> prefix are pointers to the respective
                        lemmas in the FFDB collection of glossaries.</p>
        </prefixDef>
      </listPrefixDef>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Footnotes are generally retained, but no effort has been made to link the
                    narratives mentioned in comparative notes with corresponding records within the
                    FFDB.</p>
        <p>Page numbers have been retained, but page beginnings, <gi>pb</gi>, occurring
                    within a word have been moved either before or after the word (or nominal
                    phrase) on a case to case basis, without general rule.</p>
        <normalization method="silent">
          <p>Omissions as well as supplementations by the original editor are set in
                        brackets. In all other cases, parentheses in the original are retained.</p>
          <p>Latin passages in the original (usually to mask language and themes deemed
                        indecent) are rendered in English.</p>
        </normalization>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>End-of-line hyphenation has been removed. All other hyphenation has been
                        retained.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <quotation marks="all">
          <p>All quotation marks have been retained. No effort was made to mark up
                        passages in quotation marks as, for example, <gi>q</gi>, <gi>quote</gi>, <gi>
                        said</gi>, <gi>cit</gi>, or <gi>soCalled</gi>.</p>
        </quotation>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Animals, plants, colors, characters, and place names were automatically
                        tagged using a semantic tagger based on WordNet and self-provided word
                        lists, and were subsequently checked manually. They are tagged with <gi>
                        animal</gi>, <gi>plant</gi>, <gi>color</gi>, <gi>persName</gi>, and <gi>
                        placeName</gi>, respectively.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <name type="culture" key="CNA27710">Aleut</name>
          <date notAfter="1928" notBefore="1925" type="recorded">Recorded sometime between 1925 and 1928.</date>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p>Long, long ago rich <persName>Anoogne</persName> lived in the village on <placeName>Hinchinbrook island</placeName>, keeping rough storehouses with their stone shelves <pb n="123"/>filled with valuable furs, many clothes and all kinds of native foods. He preserved many <animal>fish</animal> and eggs in the ground, for sour <animal>fish</animal> dug from the earth formed his favorite repast.</p>
      <p>All of the villages about worked for the <persName>Anoogne</persName> and often he gave feasts in his house and the guests praised him highly for his generous deeds.</p>
      <p>One evening the <persName>Anoogne</persName> took a walk on the seashore. The sky was <color>blue</color>, the sea was calm and the old man enjoyed his slow promenade. Suddenly his foot slipped and he fell. He had stepped on a dead <animal>fish</animal> cast on the beach.</p>
      <p><persName>Anoogne</persName> started to complain bitterly, but a voice came from on high, saying: "Do not scold. Do not curse the old <animal>fish</animal>. If I did not give to you the same <animal>fish</animal> for your food you will starve."</p>
      <p>"If you did not send this <animal>fish</animal>, I will not starve," the <persName>Anoogne</persName> replied.</p>
      <p>"Why not?" the voice asked.</p>
      <p>The old man told him, "I have all kinds of <animal>fish</animal>. I have all kinds of meat, enough to keep me forever. My stores are filled with <animal>halibut</animal>, <animal>seal</animal>, <animal>bear</animal>, <animal>salmon</animal>, <animal>codfish</animal>, and <animal>mountain goats</animal>. I shall not lose the food I have stored."</p>
      <p>But the voice continued, "Remember, <persName>Anoogne</persName>, very soon you shall be the most miserable man and thy riches shall not be of use to thyself."</p>
      <p>"Never, never," replied the excited <persName>Anoogne</persName>. "I am the wealthiest of the natives and I shall never grow poor."</p>
      <p>"What will you eat if your food freezes over?" he was asked.</p>
      <p>"I have dried <animal>fish</animal> and meat and have buried <animal>fish</animal> eggs, a reserve that will last a long time."</p>
      <p>"I can send the deep snow to cover the earth," he was told.</p>
      <p>"Do not think you can even cover the <plant>koongat</plant>, the edible <plant>trees</plant>?" the haughty <persName>Anoogne</persName> responded.</p>
      <p>No reply came, only repeated in gradually dying echoes, the sound of the word "ahtat."</p>
      <p>Then the big flakes of snow started to fall softly over the earth. When the <persName>Anoogne</persName> approached his house the snow was up to his knees. His food had frozen and become like paper. The old man and his helpers started to shovel the <color>white</color> blanket, <pb n="124"/>but such great flakes fell this work soon appeared useless. The snow even passed through the roof and filled the barabaras.</p>
      <p>Again came the voice from on high, "There you have it."</p>
      <p>All of the island was covered by deep snow for twenty-four months. All living <animal>creatures</animal> perished. There was no food on land, there were no <animal>fish</animal> in the sea.</p>
      <p><persName>Anoogne</persName> began to starve. Greatly did he regret his mistake and his conceit. He called his neighbors and confessed his sin.</p>
      <p>Then the voice came again, saying, "Do not speak bad words. Do not curse the food I send you. Do not grumble against fate."</p>
      <p>So ended the story of the richest old man of the ancient village of <placeName>Nutchek</placeName>.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
