<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Stolen Wife</title>
        <editor ref="p:Barnum4772" role="collector">Francis Barnum</editor>
        <editor ref="p:unidentified0" role="narrator">unidentified</editor>
        <funder>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</funder>
        <principal>
          <persName>Katja Mellmann</persName>
          <persName>Michelle Scalise Sugiyama</persName>
        </principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>XML template, digitization architecture, and automated inline tagging</resp>
          <persName>Jan Jokisch</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <extent>
        <measure unit="KB" quantity="12">About 12 kilobytes</measure>
      </extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Forager Folklore Database</authority>
        <idno type="FFDB">NNA039992</idno>
        <availability status="free">
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">CC BY</licence>
          <p>Note that the CC licence only applies to the XML file. Users should also cite the original source of the text.</p>
        </availability>
        <date when="2025">2025</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Barnum, Francis/Reed, E. Irene/Teeluk, Martha (n.d. [late 1970s]): [Stories in Barnum 1901, retranscribed and transliterated by Irene Reed and Martha Teeluk]. Ms., Alaska Native Language Archive, Elmer E. Rasmuson Library, Fairbanks, Alaska. Quot. pp. 290-291.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text digitized and encoded for use in the Forager Folklore Database. The FFDB
                    offers a basis for a systematic study of narrative universals, the evolutionary 
                    origin of storytelling, and (comparative) folklore studies.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p>The narrative was selected for being a genuine piece of oral literature recorded
                    directly, or mediated by an interpreter, from a narrator who either lived or
                    grew up as a member of a culture whose subsistence at the time of recording was,
                    or until recently had been, depending primarily on hunting, gathering, and/or
                    fishing. Care was taken to ensure the quality of the recording and the relative
                    absence of external cultural influences.</p>
      </samplingDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          <tagUsage gi="persName">Used to mark personal names (usually characters).</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="placeName">Used to mark place names.</tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="rs" occurs="9">Referencing strings are used to mark up animal names, plant names, 
                        and colors. The <att>type</att> attribute correspondingly takes one of the following 
                        values:
                        <list type="gloss"><label><val>animal</val></label><item>animal name</item><label><val>plant</val></label><item>plant name</item><label><val>color</val></label><item>color adjective or noun</item></list>
                    </tagUsage>
          <tagUsage gi="shift" occurs="25">Used to mark shifts towards a metatextual level or back to the 
                        diegesis. The <att>feature</att> attributes takes one of the following values:
                        <list type="gloss"><label><val>anamyth</val></label><item>Shift to a framing metacommentary at the beginning of a narrative.</item><label><val>apartmyth</val></label><item>Shift to a comment or aside within the course of a narration.</item><label><val>epimyth</val></label><item>Shift to a framing metacommentary at the end of a narrative.</item><label><val>diegesis</val></label><item>Shift back to the diegesis of the tale.</item></list>
                    </tagUsage>
        </namespace>
      </tagsDecl>
      <listPrefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="p" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="../references/personography.xml#$1">
          <p>Private URIs using the <code>p</code> prefix are pointers to <gi>person</gi>
                        elements in the <name type="file">personography.xml</name> file.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="q" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/$1">
          <p>URIs using the <code>q</code> prefix are <name ref="q:Q43649390">Wikidata Q
                        identifiers</name> and refer to the respective entries on <orgName ref="https://www.wikidata.org/">Wikidata</orgName>.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="g" matchPattern=".*" replacementPattern="">
          <!-- write a replacementPattern once glossaries are online -->
          <p>Private URIs using the <code>g</code> prefix are pointers to the respective
                        lemmas in the FFDB collection of glossaries.</p>
        </prefixDef>
      </listPrefixDef>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Footnotes are generally retained, but no effort has been made to link the
                    narratives mentioned in comparative notes with corresponding records within the
                    FFDB.</p>
        <p>Page numbers have been retained, but page beginnings, <gi>pb</gi>, occurring
                    within a word have been moved either before or after the word (or nominal
                    phrase) on a case to case basis, without general rule.</p>
        <normalization method="silent">
          <p>Omissions as well as supplementations by the original editor are set in
                        brackets. In all other cases, parentheses in the original are retained.</p>
          <p>Latin passages in the original (usually to mask language and themes deemed
                        indecent) are rendered in English.</p>
        </normalization>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>End-of-line hyphenation has been removed. All other hyphenation has been
                        retained.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <quotation marks="all">
          <p>All quotation marks have been retained. No effort was made to mark up
                        passages in quotation marks as, for example, <gi>q</gi>, <gi>quote</gi>, <gi>
                        said</gi>, <gi>cit</gi>, or <gi>soCalled</gi>.</p>
        </quotation>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Refer to the <gi>tagsDecl</gi>.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <name type="culture" key="CNA27735">Qaluyaarmiut</name>
          <date notAfter="1899" notBefore="1891" type="recorded">Recorded sometime between 1891 and 1899.</date>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p>So there lived a couple by a river, all alone, and likewise they had no other human companion. But that river ran out to the sea.</p>
      <p>That [her] husband, whom you recall, would go down there to the sea to hunt.</p>
      <p>Then upon arriving, he would lower those that he caught down through the window into the house, then his wife would receive them from the inside of the house, and she would skin them in the house.</p>
      <p>So that [her] husband, whom you recall, had a way of doing that all the time. And again, if he did not hunt in the sea, he would catch game from up yonder, <rs type="animal">reindeer</rs> [<rs type="animal">caribou</rs>?].</p>
      <p>And so, by and by, <shift feature="apartmyth"/>they say,<shift feature="diegesis"/> they [dual] they brought forth a child [acquired an offspring]. That [her] husband, whom you recall, didn't hunt anything much any more. They raised him well, that one you remember, not letting him lack anything. So they lived like that.</p>
      <p>And then one day, her husband went away to hunt at sea. Then, when his kayak was getting loaded there down yonder in the sea, he went home, he was about to arrive home, but somehow strangely, his wife, whom you remember, was not even in front of the house. Now then upon beaching, he got out and went up shoulder-packing his catch. Then he lowered his catch down through the window, he lowered it in vain, strangely, that one down there did not want to take it. So he pulled it out, upon looking in, <shift feature="apartmyth"/>it's said,<shift feature="diegesis"/> his wife was not there, only his child that you recall, was there all alone.</p>
      <p>So now he went down and entered. Upon entering, <shift feature="apartmyth"/>they say, <shift feature="diegesis"/>that pillow [of his] that used to be there, had been knocked down. It was evident here that a person had pulled her off the bed while she was lying in bed and dragged her out, and it was evident here [from indications] that he had brought her out.</p>
      <p>Upon going outside, <shift feature="apartmyth"/>it's said, <shift feature="diegesis"/>he could see along here that he had taken <pb n="2"/>her away, putting her in a sled. So now he went inside, got ready, putting on boots and went away following the person by his tracks, he also took along his weapons.</p>
      <p>[He traveled for so long that] Soon, <shift feature="apartmyth"/>they say, <shift feature="diegesis"/>it became winter as he was traveling on, although this journey of his from his home had started in the summertime. And also, <shift feature="apartmyth"/>they say, <shift feature="diegesis"/>it was evident that here, he had climbed up a great big high mountain. Upon reaching the peak of the mountain, <shift feature="apartmyth"/>they say, <shift feature="diegesis"/>there was another expanse of ocean down there. <shift feature="apartmyth"/>They say, <shift feature="diegesis"/>then, was a village down there by the edge of the ocean.</p>
      <p>Here, their tracks, those two, was evident that they had gone down.</p>
      <p>Upon arriving there, to the said village, <shift feature="apartmyth"/>they say, <shift feature="diegesis"/>was an old man chopping outdoors. So then he asked him about that one, concerning his wife, as to where she had gone. It is said that he said he [another] had took her to the other side of the ocean. Now then that old man whom we recall, took a <rs type="animal">king salmon</rs> and chopped it, and its inside there was hollow, so now as it was finished, he then took it to the water, then the old man ordered that man to get aboard. Then when he boarded, he covered the rear. So now it went away via down under the water, but then upon reaching the other side, it surfaced through the other side. So now down yonder from the village, upon getting out, he went up after turning his transporter downwards. Upon going up, he found that there was dancing inside the community house [sounds of dancing emanating from the qasgiq]. But his wife was in another house separate from the others with the portal shut. So he entered smashing the portal and took his wife, bringing her down, he put her into that transporter of his and took her away. So to that, which is remembered, to the other side they landed and furthermore, they got out, and upon getting out, they pushed that out, which we <pb n="3"/>recall, that which was their transport and it became a <rs type="animal">king salmon</rs> and swam away. And then they went home [returned] using their trail.</p>
      <p>Upon taking notice, <shift feature="apartmyth"/>they say, <shift feature="diegesis"/>as they were approaching their house, there were <rs type="animal">animals</rs> of various kinds coming out of his house. It was found that, <shift feature="apartmyth"/>it's said, <shift feature="diegesis"/>the <rs type="animal">animals</rs> had raised that whom it is recalled, their child while they were gone. It was found that their child, we remember, had become an <rs type="animal">animal</rs>. And they, since they did not want to stay there without their child, went away and became <rs type="animal">animals</rs> themselves, they turned into <rs type="animal">wolverines</rs>, <shift feature="apartmyth"/>they say, <shift feature="diegesis"/>that couple.</p>
      <p><shift feature="epimyth"/>Iaugiuq.<note>archaic closing formula the meaning of which is lost; cf. Barnum 1901, p. 272.</note></p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
